Simon Kapitza

Quantitative & Applied Ecology Group (QAEco)
The University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, 3010

 \square +61 412 914 876 \bowtie simon.kapitza@student.unimelb.edu.au

♥ @simonkapitza 😭 Blog 🗘 GitHub

I am a global change ecologist researching interactions between socioeconomic and biophysical drivers of biodiversity change. My key strength is in interdisciplinary thinking to understand, capture and predict the impact of global transitions of the anthropocene on ecosystems, biodiversity and species.

Skills

Data Analysis	Proficient R user with experience in knitr, sweave, and RMarkdown, as well as integration of basic C++ via the RCpp package. Particularly experienced with very large spatial data sets and parallel processing (MaxEnt, Regression Trees, Linear Mixed Models). GitHub for version control. Intermediate experience with Python, SQL, ArcGIS, QGIS.
Leadership skills	Initiating and leading interdisciplinary research in our most recent project. Currently planning research collaborations with institutes in Europe, with three scheduled seminars.
Languages	German ●●● English ●●● Spanish ●●○ French ●○○
Education	
2017 - present	PhD - Science University of Melbourne
	Supervisors: Prof Brendan Wintle, Dr Nick Golding Project: Global integrated assessment of biophysical and socioeconomic drivers of biodiversity change
2013 - 2016	MSc - Environmental Sciences (High Distinction), Albert-Ludwigs-Universitaet Freiburg Supervisors: Prof Carsten Dormann, Prof Brendan Wintle
	Project: Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Australian Great Desert Skinks under a changing fire regime (in collaboration with QAEco)
2009 - 2013	BSc Hon - Environmental Science and Politics University of Stirling Supervisor: Prof Daisy Dent
	Project: Rural Livelihoods in Changing Contexts: Causes and Impacts of Deforestation in Ta Veaeng District, Cambodia
2011 - 2012	Study Abroad University of Sydney
Presentations	
2018	Integrating drivers of change: an assessment of bio-physical and socio-economic climate
	change impacts on species habitat Australian Ecological Society Conference, Brisbane
	British Ecological Society Annual Meeting, Birmingham
	Accounting for socio-economic impacts in biodiversity modelling
	British Ecological Society Quantitative Ecology Spatial Interest Group conference, St. Andrews Assessing direct and indirect impacts of climate change on bird habitat
	Poster, International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews
	Indirect impacts of climate change on future bird habitat in Vietnam and Australia
	PhD confirmation seminar, School of BioSciences, University of Melbourne
	Comparing the biophysical and economic impacts of climate change on biodiversity Visiting scholar seminar, Helmholtz Institute for Zoology and Wildlife Research, Berlin
2017	Accounting for socioeconomic drivers of biodiversity change: A novel integrated assessment framework
	Seminar, Quantitative & Applied Ecology Group, University of Melbourne
2016	Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Great Desert Skinks under a changing fire regime
	MSc completion seminar, School of BioSciences, University of Melbourne
Workshops	
2019	CBRI Grand Challenges
2018	University of Melbourne Computational Biology Research Initiative Spatial Point Pattern Analysis
2010	Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence for Mathematical and Statistical Frontiers Combining Different Data Types In a Single Model International Statistical Ecology Conference 2018

Publications

Kapitza, S., Golding, N., Improved spatially-explicit land-use change modelling to predict future land use and biodiversity outcomes (in prep)

Kapitza, S., Ha, P. V., Kompas, T, Cadenhead, N. C. R, Bal, P., Golding, N., Wintle, B.A., An integrated assessment of the direct biophysical and indirect socio-economic impacts of climate change on biodiversity (in prep)

Kapitza, S., Cadenhead, N., Wintle, B., Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Great Desert Skinks under a changing fire regime (in prep)

Awards and scholarships

2018	Wiley Award for Best Poster, International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews
	Science Abroad Travelling Scholarship, University of Melbourne (AUD 1500)
	Financial Support for Research or Conference Travel, University of Melbourne (AUD 2000)
	Drummond Travel Award (AUD 1500)
2017	Australian Research Council Discovery top-up grant (AUD 21,000)
	Melbourne International Research Scholarship (AUD 120,000)
2015	DAAD PROMOS Scholarship grant (2300 EUR)

Academic activities

2019 - present	Orygen Youth Health International Student Welfare Project Peer leader
2018 - present	British Ecological Society Quantitative Ecology Special Interest Committee Member
2017 - present	QAEco Diversity and Inclusion Group Committee Member
2017	QAEco mentoring scheme Organiser
2015 - 2016	Staff-Student Consultative Committee, University of Freiburg Student Rep

Professional experience

2016 - present	Research Assistant Dr Luke Kelly and Prof Brendan Wintle (University of Melbourne)
2014 - 2015	Research Assistant Fraunhofer Institute for Solar Energy Systems
2012 - 2013	Social Media Manager Creative Stirling
2012	Intern German Embassy Colombo
2011	Intern German Agro Action e.V. Cambodia
2008 - 2009	Workshop coordinator Youth Educational Institute Jugendbildungsstaette Juist

Societies

British Ecological Society, Australian Ecological Society, BUND (Friends of the Earth Germany)

Referees

Dr Nick GoldingPhD Supervisor Research Fellow QAEco University of Melbourne nicholas.golding@unimelb.edu.au

Melbourne, March 25, 2019 Simon Kapitza